Finding Aid for Michigan Schoolmasters' Club
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Michigan Schoolmasters' Club records 1886-1969
Michigan Schoolmasters' Club
1 linear ft.
87242 Bimu N201 2
The records of the Michigan Schoolmaster' Club at the University of Michigan contain historical information, administrative files, and correspondence.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was donated by the Michigan Schoolmasters' Club in 1969 (Donor # 4808 ).
The record group is open to researchers.
The Michigan Schoolmaster' Club was founded in 1886 at the University of Michigan when a group of forward thinking "schoolmen" gathered together to discuss the feasability of forming a teacher's club with the purpose of extending and improving the professional relationship between educators on the secondary and collegiate levels. Among those who encouraged and participated in the formation of this group were James B. Angell and John Dewey.
For the first seven years of its existence, meetings of the Schoolmasters' Club were held three times a year. As this arrangement became impractical, it was agreed that one meeting a year would suffice. These annual meetings were held on the campus of the University of Michigan at Ann Arbor until 1969, with the only break being the year 1945 when permission for the meeting was refused by the federal government. The format for the annual meeting was consistent: general sessions were held in the morning and a variety of conferences on specific academic subjects were held in the afternoon. Speakers for the general sessions were local and national figures in the field of education. The club published the proceedings of the annual meeting in its journal from 1894 onward.
In 1965 and 1968, the Schoolmasters' Club undertook the planning of a series of "Articulation Workshops" which were held at various junior and community colleges in Michigan. The aim of these workshops was to identify problems common to secondary and collegiate level educators and then to work towards possible solutions.
As attendence at the annual meetings and membership waned in the second half of the century, it became clear that the Schoolmasters' Club would need either to rethink its mission or fade out of existence. Several alternative options were discussed by the executive committee. It was decided in 1969 that remaining funds should be used to establish a scholarship fund at the University of Michigan in the name of the Michigan Schoolmasters' Club.
The records of the Michigan Schoolmasters' Club (MSC) provide a good source of information about current educational issues in the period from 1886 to 1969. The collection has been arranged into three series: Historical/Background Files, Administrative Records, and Correspondence.
Subjects:
Michigan Schoolmasters' Club.; Teachers--Michigan.
- Historical/Background Files
  The Historical/Background Files series includes surveys relating to the articulation workshops in 1965 and 1968, background material used in the preparation of a published history of the MSC, several journal papers, life membership lists, and a file concerning the dissolution of the Club.
  Additional materials at the Bentley concerning the Michigan Schoolmasters' Club include the club's programs, proceedings, and journals, which are bound chronologically from 1902, and the history of the first seven decades of the club, published in 1958 by Leslie Butler. These materials are cataloged separately in the published materials catalog of the library.
  - Articulation Workshops, 1965-1968 (Box 1)
  - Background Material for History of MSC, 1950-1958 (Box 1)
  - Journal Papers, 1960-1964 (Box 1)
  - Life Membership Lists, 1950-1963 (Box 1)
  - Papers concerning Dissolution of MSC, 1969 (Box 1)
- Administrative Records
  The Administrative Records consist of a bound volume of meeting minutes, membership lists, and the original articles of association (1886-1922), a file of presidents' letters, a subseries of Committee Minutes, and the records of several of the Club's sections.
  - Records of MSC, 1886-1922, 1 volume (Box 1)
  - Financial Records and Minutes, 1935-1964 (Box 1)
  - Presidents' Letters, 1956-1963 (Box 1)
  - Committee Minutes
    - Executive Committee, 1967-1969 (Box 1)
    - Planning Committee, 1964-1968 (Box 1)
    - Various Reports
      - Appraisal (Box 1)
      - Auditing, 1963-1968 (Box 1)
      - Resolutions, 1961-1966 (Box 1)
      - Teachers Agencies, 1922, 1952 (Box 1)
  - Section Records
    - Fine Arts, 1930-1950 (Box 1)
    - Mathematics, 1935-1967 (Box 1)
    - Music, 1930-1945 (Box 1)
  - Visiting Teachers Program, 1926-1929, 2 folders (Box 1)
- Correspondence, 1918-1921, 1960-1969
  The Correspondence files are arranged chronologically from 1918 to 1969, with a significant gap from 1921 to 1960.
  - 1918-1921 (Box 1)
  - 1960-1963 (Box 1)
  - 1963-1964 (Box 1)
  - 1964-1965 (Box 1)
  - 1965-1966 (Box 1)
  - 1966-1967 (Box 1)
  - 1968-1969 (Box 1)
- Sound recordings (Box 1)
  - Audiotapes, 1969, 2 reels; 7-inch reels, 3-3/4ips (Box 1)